Finding Aid for Marie D. Hartwig Papers 1927-1988
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Marie D. Hartwig Papers 1927-1988
Hartwig, Marie Dorothy, 1906-
90151 Aa/2
Instructor and professor of physical education, 1930-1977, and first director of women's athletics, 1972-1976, at the University of Michigan. Papers document the history of physical education and recreational sports for women and the development of women's varsity athletics at the university as well as Hartwig's involvement in various professional associations and her work with recreation programs at Interlochen Music Camp.
6 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The pre-1993 accessions were donated by Marie D. Hartwig in June 1988, April 1989, November 1992, and December 1992. The 1998 accessions were donated by Marie D. Hartwig, through Sheryl Szady, in three installments in April and May 1998. Donor no. 5252
The collection is open for research.
Marie Dorothy Hartwig was born on August 1, 1906 in East Orange, New Jersey. She attended Detroit Northwestern High School and did undergraduate work at the University of Michigan, where she received an A.B. degree in Fine Arts in 1929. Thereafter, she worked at the newly opened Michigan League, advancing from desk clerk in 1929 to secretary to manager in 1930. She became an instructor in the Department of Physical Education for Women (DPEW) in 1930. She remained a student at the University of Michigan and completed her B.S.Ed. degree in physical education in 1932 and her M.A. degree in the same subject in 1938. She was promoted to associate supervisor at the DPEW in 1942, to supervisor in 1951, to associate professor in 1968, and to professor in 1969. When the DPEW joined the Department of Physical Education for Men to form the Department of Physical Education in 1970, Hartwig was made a professor, and remained in this capacity until her retirement in 1976. She has been professor emerita since 1977.
Marie Hartwig was also very active in summer programs of the University of Michigan. She was an instructor in DPEW summer sessions from 1931 to 1938 and from 1940 to 1943. She also worked with the National Music Camp at Interlochen, Michigan, serving on the Counselor Education staff from 1944 until 1948 and as the director of the Counselor Education Program from 1949 until 1982.
Hartwig was active in a wide variety of organizations pertaining directly or indirectly to her professional work in physical education. These included the Ann Arbor Club of Michigan Alumnae (1939-1984), the Michigan Education Association (1939-1957), the National Education Association (1939-1957), the Michigan Camping Association (1949-1968), the American Camping Association (1949-1968), the Ann Arbor Figure Skating Club (1941-1957), and the Michigan Women's Athletic Association. She held offices in many of these as well as other organizations. For example, she was a member of the Ann Arbor Community Center Board (1979-1982), of the Board of Directors of the United Fund (1959-1962), and of the Board of Directors of the Michigan League (1980-1987).
Marie Hartwig also gave speeches and other presentations to a wide range of groups. She published articles, manuals, and books, and served as the editor of the periodical Sportslight from 1939 to 1949. A list of her degrees, appointments, organization memberships, presentations, and publications has been placed in the Biography folder in box 1.
The Hartwig papers are organized into contain four series:
Instructional, Publications, and Biographical Material -- Boxes 1, 4
University of Michigan Files -- Boxes 1-2, 5
Camp Activities -- Boxes 2-3, 5-6
Audio Material -- Box 3
The finding aid brings together all files for each series regardless of which accession they were received in. As a result, the box numbers may not always be in sequential order.
The papers of Marie Hartwig consist of 6 linear feet of material and one oversize volume concerning the career, activities, and thought of Marie ("Pete") Hartwig. The papers document Hartwig's wide range of activities as educator, coach and women's athletics administrator at the University of Michigan and her work with the recreation program at the National Music Camp at Interlochen, Michigan.
The papers contain material relating to the history of women's physical education, recreation and athletics at the University of Michigan from the 1930s to 1980s; the history of recreational activities and the Camper Education Program at the National Music Camp in Interlochen, Michigan from the 1940s to 1980s; and the evolution of Hartwig's ideas about instruction in sports, the training of counselors and management of recreational camps, and recreational programs for children and adults.
Subjects:
Hartwig, Marie Dorothy, 1906-; Michigan League.; Physical education for women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Recreation--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physical Education for Women.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Women's Athletic Association.; Athletes--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; College teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women athletes--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Field hockey.; Hartwig, Marie Dorothy, 1906-; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Students--1951-1960.; Women.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Instructional, Publications, and Biographical Material
  The Instructional, Publications, and Biographical Material series documents Marie Hartwig's activities as an author and teacher. The bulk of this series consists of Hartwig's handouts, curricular plans, and student assignments for classes she taught at the University of Michigan. School work from the 1930s and instructional material from the 1930s to the 1970s show the development of her ideas and methods. This series documents the more personal aspects of her career and intellectual life, yet complements materials in the other two series that document her role and impact at the University of Michigan and the National Music Camp in Interlochen, Michigan.
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Curriculum outlines and plans (Box 1)
  - Women's physical education, University of Michigan 1932-1967 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan, Division of Physical Education 1984-1987 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan, Physical education courses 1932-1936 (Box 1)
  - Community recreation class, teaching materials
    - 1944-1957 (Box 1)
    - 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 1)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 1)
    - Clippings and pamphlets (Box 1)
  - Fencing instructional material 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Golf instructional material
    - 1960-1968 (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 1)
  - Instructional handouts (Box 1)
  - Instructional materials, typed (binder) (Box 1)
  - Camp Counselor Training Workbook (Hartwig/Peterson), Fifth Printing 1954 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous instructional materials (Box 1)
  - Student papers 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Programming workshop: The Center for Research on Learning and Teaching, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Staff Handbook 1961-1962 (Binder) (Box 1)
  - Publication correspondence (Box 1)
  - Articles (Box 4)
  - Badminton (Box 4)
  - Biographical Photographs and Clippings (Box 4)
  - Committees and Appointments (Box 4)
  - Golf
    - Instruction (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook (Box 4)
    - Service Class Outlines and Evaluation Methods (Box 4)
  - Master of Arts Thesis: "An Experimental Study of Fundamental Coaching Factors Influencing the Learning of the Golf Swing," 1938 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Correspondence (Box 4)
    - Instructional Material (Box 4)
    - Notes (Box 4)
  - Organized Camping Class (Box 4)
  - Organization and Administration Class (Box 4)
  - Paper: "Tests and Measurements," 1932 (Box 4)
  - Publications
    - Clippings (Box 4)
    - Correspondence (Box 4)
    - Press Releases and Brochures (Box 4)
  - Recreational Leadership
    - Handouts and Plans (Box 4)
    - Students' Notebooks (Box 4)
    - Workbook (Box 4)
  - School Work 1932-1933, 1936 (Box 4)
  - Tap Dancing (Box 4)
  - Theory of Rhythms Class (Box 4)
- University of Michigan Files
  The University of Michigan Files series is highlighted by information about Marie Hartwig's work with the Michigan Women's Athletic Association. Materials about the Michigan League's history and Marie Hartwig's service on its Board of Governors from 1980 to 1987 are also included. Box 2 contains material--including copies of programs--concerning Lantern Night, Spring Weekend, and Michigras, all student activities in which the DPEW participated.
  The University of Michigan Files series documents Hartwig's activities as a faculty member, administrator, committee member, and advisor at the University of Michigan. Hartwig's active role in the DPEW is well represented, particularly in respect to the construction of new athletic facilities, revision of the curriculum, establishment of staff standards, and methods of evaluation. Other materials show Hartwig organizing conferences, intramurals, and intercollegiate athletics. This series also contains reports, financial records, and correspondence from the Women's Athletic Association, which Hartwig advised. Also of interest are statistical data gathered under Hartwig's direction about women's recreation in the 1930s and 1960s. Furthermore, this series contains materials Hartwig came to possess from the DPEW, its staff, and the Women's Athletic Building, but which is not directly related to her activities.
  - Intramurals 1949-1968 (Box 1)
  - Physical recreation survey, University of Michigan 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Recreation survey 1963-1965 (Box 1)
  - Recreation leadership, University of Michigan (Box 1)
  - Recreational leadership (Box 1)
  - Campus leadership (Box 1)
  - Recognition awards (Box 1)
    (includes Hartwig scholarship)
  - Women's varsity sports, University of Michigan 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Women's Athletic Association
    - 1939-1954 (Box 1)
    - 1979 (Box 1)
    - 1980 (Box 1)
    - 1981 (Box 1)
    - 1982 (Box 2)
    - 1983 (Box 2)
    - 1984 (Box 2)
    - 1985 (Box 2)
    - 1986 (Box 2)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - M-Women 1985-1988 (Box 2)
  - Michigan League
    - Miscellaneous materials concerning the League and its history (Box 2)
    - Scheduled events (Box 2)
    - By-laws (Box 2)
    - Financial affairs (Box 2)
    - Cookbook committee (Box 2)
    - Board of Governors
      - 1978-1980 (Box 2)
      - 1981 (Box 2)
      - 1982 (Box 2)
      - 1983 (Box 2)
      - 1984 (Box 2)
      - 1985 (Box 2)
      - 1986 (Box 2)
      - 1987 (Box 2)
    - Alumnae Council (Box 2)
    - Other (Box 2)
  - Margaret Waterman alumnae group (Box 2)
  - Ann Arbor Community Center, Board of Directors 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - American Camping Association 1964-1966 (Box 2)
  - Golf club (Box 2)
  - Women's Professional Golf Association (Box 2)
  - Lantern Night (Box 2)
  - Michigras (includes two copies of a photograph record) (Box 2)
  - Spring Weekend (Box 2)
  - Michifish (Box 2)
  - Programs (miscellaneous) (Box 2)
  - Advisory Committee on Recreation, Intramurals, and Club Sports (ACRICS) and Building Planning Subcommittees 1973 undated (Box 4)
  - Committee on Reorganization of Physical Education for Men and Women 1968 (Box 4)
  - Department of Physical Education
    - Annual Report Contribution 1970 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda 1970 (Box 4)
    - Dance Proposal 1973 (Box 4)
    - Physical Education Review Committee 1974-1975 (Box 4)
    - Professional Program 1972-1974 (Box 4)
  - Department of Physical Education for Women
    - Building Committee 1954-1955 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence of Former Staff 1955-1968, undated (Box 4)
    - Curriculum 1967-1970 (Box 4)
    - Dance Programs 1934-1952 (Box 4)
    - Foreign Visitors 1948-1967 (Box 4)
    - Michigan College Women's Physical Education Teachers Conference
      - 1953-1960 (Box 4)
      - 1961 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Photographs, 1943-1944 (Box 4)
    - Physical Education and Recreation Indoor Facilities
      - Preliminary Recommendations and Statistics 1967-1969 (Box 4)
      - Reports 1967-1969, undated (Box 4)
    - Proficiency and Appraisal 1968-1969, undated (Box 4)
    - Projected Needs 1964-1965 (Box 4)
    - Recreation Survey 1963-1964
      - Final Report (Box 4)
      - Senior Seminar Materials (Box 4)
    - Service Program
      - 1966-1968 (Box 4)
      - Instructor's Handbook (Box 4)
    - Staff Handbook 1967-1969 (Box 4)
    - Teaching Loads 1967, 1969 (Box 4)
  - Marie Hartwig Fund 1976 (Box 5)
  - National Conference on Women's Sports: Ethics and the Amateur Principle 1974-1976 (Box 5)
  - Palmer Field (Box 5)
  - Physical Education Surveys 1932, 1934 undated (Box 5)
  - Questionnaire Requests (Box 5)
  - Residence halls (Box 5)
  - Women of the University Faculty 1970-1971 (Box 5)
  - Women's Athletic Association
    - 1949-1957 (Box 5)
    - 1964-1969 (Box 5)
    - Constitution and History (Box 5)
    - Crop and Saddle Riding Club 1961-1964 (Box 5)
    - Financial Records 1947-1969 (Volume 1)
    - Lantern Night
      - 1934, 1940-1944, undated (Box 5)
      - 1952-1953 (Box 5)
    - Michigras
      - 1936-1940 (Box 5)
      - 1946-1947 (Box 5)
      - 1947-1948 (Box 5)
      - 1951-1957 (Box 5)
      - 1957-1958 (Box 5)
      - 1959-1964 (Box 5)
    - Michilodeon 1946 (Box 5)
    - Swimming Pool Project 1937 (Box 5)
    - Style Show 1938 (Box 5)
  - Women's Athletic Building
    - Rentals 1935-1950 (Box 5)
    - Repairs and Requests 1945-1956 (Box 5)
  - Women's Intercollegiate Athletics
    - Advisory Council Minutes 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda 1974-1976 (Box 5)
  - Women's Intramurals
    - 1928-1934, undated (Box 5)
    - 1935-1948 (Box 5)
    - 1966-1968, undated (Box 5)
- Camp Activities
  The Camp Activities series primarily contains material relating to Hartwig's work with the National Music Camp in Interlochen, Michigan. Part of this series documents Hartwig's instrumental role in the establishment and supervision of the Counselor Education Program. Valuable materials include correspondence, statements of purpose, instructional materials, brochures, and students' evaluations of their experiences. Other materials in the series resulted from Hartwig's activities as camp coordinator, such as the selection of counseling staff, planning of pre-camp workshops for directors and counselors, and supervision of division and recreation directors. Numerous materials show Hartwig's interest in camp recreation. Photographs document recreational activities of campers and counselors-in-training in the 1950s and 1960s. Her records about social and recreational activities for campers present another perspective of campers' experiences at the National Music Camp, outside of their musical or artistic pursuits. The Bentley Historical Library also holds the records of the Interlochen Center for the Arts, which include material about the National Music Camp.
  - National Music Camp, Interlochen, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - National Music Camp, Counselor training program (Box 3)
  - Camp director's institute (Box 3)
  - Camp director's institute, correspondence 1965-1966 (Box 3)
  - Day camp in recreational leadership 1962-1969 (Box 3)
  - Camping, miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Counselor education (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Camp Directors Institute 1966 (Box 5)
  - Day Camp in Recreational Leadership (Box 5)
  - National Music Camp
    - All-Camp Senate Meetings 1973-1974, 1977-1978 (Box 5)
    - Camp Coordinator's Reports 1966-1967, 1972 (Box 5)
    - Camp Directors' Meetings 1967-1980 (Box 5)
    - Camp Directors' Reports
      - 1951 (Box 5)
      - 1967 (Box 5)
      - 1973 (Box 5)
      - 1976 (Box 5)
      - 1977 (Box 5)
      - 1978 (Box 5)
    - Coordination of Personnel and Cabins
      - 1951-1969 (Box 5)
      - 1970 (Box 5)
      - 1971 (Box 5)
      - 1972 (Box 5)
      - 1973-1978 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda
      - 1943-1953 (Box 5)
      - 1954-1958 (Box 5)
      - 1962-1970 (Box 5)
      - 1971-1975 (Box 5)
      - 1976-1982 (Box 5)
    - Counselor Education Program
      - 1944-1949 (Box 6)
      - Applications 1968-1969 (Box 6)
      - Brochures (Box 6)
      - Counselor-in-Training Report 1981 (Box 6)
      - Counselors' case studies (Box 6)
      - Instructional Materials, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Photographs (Box 6)
      - Purpose and Evaluation Methods 1957-1981 (Box 6)
      - Reports and Recommendations 1953-1954 (Box 6)
      - Student Testimonials (Box 6)
      - Survey: "Events for Best Learning," 1954 (Box 6)
    - Looking at Interlochen's Future and Expansion (L.I.F.E.) Committee 1968-1969 (Box 6)
    - Job Descriptions and Counselor's Manuals, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous Reports (Box 6)
    - Pre-and Post-Tests for Counselors 1967 (Box 6)
    - Pre-Camp Counselor Workshop (Box 6)
    - Recreation
      - Craft Department
        - 1972 undated (Box 6)
        - 1977 (Box 6)
      - "Museum Pieces" Newsletter (Box 6)
      - Philosophy and Objectives 1974-1975 (Box 6)
      - Photographs, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Reports and Inventories (Box 6)
      - 1944 (Box 6)
      - 1945 (Box 6)
      - 1947 (Box 6)
      - 1948 (Box 6)
      - 1949 (Box 6)
      - 1951 (Box 6)
      - 1952 (Box 6)
      - 1953 (Box 6)
      - 1954 (Box 6)
      - 1955-1957 (Box 6)
      - 1971 (Box 6)
      - 1975 (Box 6)
      - 1976 (Box 6)
      - 1978 (Box 6)
      - Social Activities (Box 6)
      - Trips (Box 6)
- Audio Material
  The Audio Material series contains nineteen audio cassettes, sixteen of which document the National Conference on Women Sports: Ethics and the Amateur Principle. The conference was organized by Hartwig and held at the University of Michigan in 1975.
  - Audio Cassettes (19), include 16 tapes of The National Conference on Women's Sports: Ethics and the Amateur Principle 1975 (Box 3)
Related Material
Additional sources at the Bentley Library containing information about Marie Hartwig include:
University of Michigan Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics, Records.
University of Michigan. Women's Athletics.
Records include material from Hartwig's tenure as director of women's athletics.
"The History of Intercollegiate Athletics for Women at the University of Michigan,"
a 1987 University of Michigan doctoral dissertation by Sheryl Marie Szady, includes an extensive discussion of Marie Hartwig's role in the development of women's athletics at the university.
Interlochen Center for the Arts
, which includes material about the National Music Camp.